Hello and welcome back to another episode
with ItsDrDan and today we're going to be
learning about the structure of proteins.
Specifically, we're going to be
diving into all the different types
of ways that we can classify and
understand the structure of a protein.
So we're going to go step by step
building up our proteins starting
from the amino acid sequence.
Then going through all the individual
intermolecular forces for how the
structure can be organized, help
stabilize itself, and then eventually
we'll go into all the kinds of different
interactions that can try to stabilize
with the environment that it's around.
So we'll go through it step by step.
This is a very introductory biochemistry
video, so it's not going to go into
too crazy, graduate level, senior
level detail, but just enough so
you can understand the basics.
So let's take a look and let's dive into
all these different types of structures.
Okay, so the first thing that we're going
to be looking at is the primary structure.
So what that is, is when we are
looking at the individual sequence of
amino acids that are bonded together.
Now, when we look at one of these
sequences, usually what you're
going to be looking at is different
structures that could be drawn either
like an expanded structural formula
where it's very linear, kind of 90
degrees, or you might see it where
it's in that zigzag skeletal notation.
Personally, I like to draw it
this way because it makes it
a little bit easier to follow.
So when we're looking at the
backbone of it, the big thing is,
is that it's a linear chain, meaning
that it's in one continuous line.
Now when we look at that, you'll see
that it's in the same repeating pattern.
It always starts at the
end terminal, right?
So where the amino group is.
Then from there, it's always going to
go from the left to right to where the
C terminal is or where the carboxylic
acid is at the very end of that chain.
Now, it always goes from left to right
because each carbon that is in the middle
of each amino acid is considered to be the
alpha carbon, meaning that has chirality
to it because you have four different
groups around each one of those carbons.
So each one of these where you see
an R attached to it, That's where the
alpha carbon is, like, right above it.
So we have a couple of them
on this particular one.
So now when we look at this, each
amino acid is called a residue,
meaning that each one is unique.
It has potentially these
different unique characteristics.
So you see these R
groups attached to them.
meaning that they have these different
side chains that are attached to each one.
Now, when we're looking at the sequence,
you'll see that it has this repeating
pattern, so you'll keep seeing the same
pattern of NCC repeating in the structure.
So when I see that N Then you got C, C,
so we got N, C, C, N, C, C, and it'll
keep going as it's bound together.
Now each of those different residues
or amino acids, they're each
bound together via a peptide bond.
So you'll see I have these
peptide bonds in green here.
So just to kind of help highlight
them a little bit, it's the
same thing as an amide, right?
So if you think back to organic
chemistry, so that amide was the
double bond with the nitrogen, you're
looking for the exact same thing.
So if you're an organic chemist and
you're more in favor of that instead
of biochem, look for the amides.
So being that we have
that repeating pattern.
The thing about that is that's what
we consider to be the backbone of it.
So that repeating nitrogen, carbon,
carbon, that is where we talk when
we say backbone, referring to that.
Now, when we talk about those
amino acids, the way that you can
organize them is we like to describe
them based on polarity, right?
So if it's polar or nonpolar, or
if we want to switch to biochem
talk, hydrophilic or hydrophobic.
So are you, are we loving water
or, or are we afraid of water?
Right?
How exactly do we want to look at that
after that's how acidic or basic is it?
So is it something that, um, has a
carboxylic acid on it or is it something
that has an amino group on the chains?
So when we're looking at those
different amino acids, we can organize
all the different amino acids by
the different properties of it.
So it all starts with hydrophobic,
hydrophilic, So when we're looking
at all of them, right, we have
20 amino acids that exist, right?
So 20 essential amino acids that
are essential for your metabolism,
nine of them are hydrophobic.
So that includes glycine, alanine, valine,
leucine, isoleucine, phenylalanine,
methionine, proline, and tryptophan.
Now the hydrophilic ones,
which are water loving, right?
So because we have that, that love
for water, right, they're polar, they
can be separated based on their pH.
So if it's acidic, that means that it must
have a carboxylic acid attached to it.
So when we have the carboxylic acid
group that's attached to that structure,
and we're talking about the R group
itself, so where the special feature
is, then it's going to be acidic because
it has the ability to donate a proton.
If it's basic, that must mean that when
we think of basic organic groups, This
has to have an amine attached to it.
Okay, so basic has an amine,
acidic has a carboxylic acid.
So you're looking for those.
Now, when it's considered to
be neutral, that's generally
anything that's just polar.
So usually anything with alcohols,
amides, uh, are the most common
ones that you're going to be seeing.
So if you're looking for any of
those different things that usually
can do hydrogen bonding or dipole
dipole interactions, if you want
to think of intermolecular forces.
So talking about intermolecular
forces, let's now dive into what
kind of forces are these different
amino acids capable and how can our
structure continue to evolve when we
want to look beyond just the order that
these individual things are bound in.
How can that change?
Um, especially as the structure continues
to grow and get bigger and bigger.
So now the most important feature
is when the chain starts growing,
being that it has a geometry to it.
So there's tetrahedral and
there's trigonal pyramidal and
trigonal planar geometries that
are being seen in the structure.
What's going to happen?
It's going to start folding and bending
now, and especially because this
molecule is getting very large, right?
If you talk in 10, 20, 30, 100, hundreds
of amino acids long, It's going to start
kind of folding and bending and it's
going to get very, very long, very long.
Kind of think of it as if you take
like, like sheets off your bed and
you were to tie them together, right?
And you had like 50 sheets and
you tied them all together.
Well, eventually you're, how are you
going to be carrying, if you wanted
to carry the whole pile, it's going
to lead to this giant clump of sheets.
Well, it's kind of sort of a similar idea
of whether that's a good analogy or not.
It's, it's following the same thing.
So what's going to happen
is the secondary structure.
So the next level of organization
is as this thing folds, it can
start hydrogen bonding to itself.
And the reason for that is because on
the structure, there are amino groups.
And then there's carbonyl
groups on it, meaning there is
nitrogen groups and CO groups.
So what's going to happen is the
amino group is a hydrogen bond donor,
meaning it has the hydrogen part that's
participating in the hydrogen bond.
And it's going to hydrogen bond to
the carbonyl on the opposite side.
So if you kind of remember how we would
label things like that, right, we'd say
delta negative plus, delta negative plus.
So we have that acceptor
donor relationship.
So now that when this occurs is
because that polypeptide that we're
making as you increase amino acids,
it's going to start folding on itself.
And the reason it wants to do this
is for stability, is to help protect
the protein and also serve as.
As help, it's function as well.
Every protein has a specific shape,
so it does a specific feature.
It can bond to specific things.
It does specific things.
So stability and function.
So the way that these can look and
look in a couple different ways.
So the first one is in a helical pattern.
So with this one, if you can
kind of imagine this as like a
kind of like a ribbon that's sort
of like spinning around, right?
So this is spinning, spinning
and spinning and spinning.
So the alpha helix, the way that
this works is essentially you'll have
all those hydrogen bonds that are
happening where about every fourth
amino acid, you'll have a hydrogen
bond that's occurring in this chain.
So you're going to see all these
little pink, little hydrogen bonds
within the structure that's going to be
forming between all those amino groups.
And the carbonyls now, as this is
twisting together, it helps kind of, it
puts all the R groups on the outside so
that way they can interact and kind of
even do further interactions around it.
So it allows it to have this ability
to either connect to different proteins
maybe, um, or maybe potentially
connect on different sides of it.
So that way there's different shapes
and different abilities that can form.
So that was the alpha helix.
Now, the other option that could
occur is the beta pleated sheet.
So that the way that this one
works is it's kind of like a zigzag
pattern that keeps kind of happening.
So it keeps zigzagging,
then it wraps around.
And what we're seeing here is we'll
see those hydrogen bond interactions.
That are occurring across the
sheet so that in order to help
bring those together, so it's
protected from anything foreign
that could eventually take it apart.
So we have these two different
shapes that help do it.
Now the thing to point out is that this
is between the backbone of it, right?
It's not our groups that
are talking to each other.
It's only the pieces of the backbone that
are interacting versus our next structure.
So in our next structure, the
tertiary structure, this is when
the side of chains are going to
start to interact with each other.
And the big idea here is that there's
going to be this spatial arrangement of
the amino acids that are going to happen.
So once you start kind of having those
spiral patterns, and especially when
the amino acid gets really, really big.
Then you're going to have side
chains that can interact with each
other across hundreds of amino acids
away because it's folding so much.
And those R groups are polar as well.
So what they can do is they can do all
kinds of non covalent interactions, a.
k.
a.
intermolecular forces, where
they can interact with each
other to help stabilize.
Now they can also make bonds
as well, so there's five major
interactions that the R groups can do.
There's hydrophobic
interactions, meaning non-polar.
So think, um, either dispersion,
London, dispersion, vanderwahl
forces, whatever you learned them by.
That's what we mean by hydrophobic
hydrogen bonding, right?
So if you remember, it has to be, um, an
oxygen, nitrogen, or a flooring attached
to hydrogen, and then salt bridges.
So we'll talk about what that
means, A diss, sulfide linkage,
and a hydrophilic interaction.
So now when we like to think about these,
so let's start with kind of the first
one, which is hydrophobic and also kind
of feeding into hydrophilic as well.
So when we're talking about proteins,
almost all of them, you got to
think where are they located?
They're inside your body, right?
So inside the cells in your body,
what are you mainly made up of?
You're 70 percent made of water, right?
So meaning your proteins are in a aqueous
environment, meaning made of water, right?
So what happens to those nonpolar
molecules when you put them in water?
Well, if you ever dropped oil into
water, well, what kind of happens?
Well, even if you try to kind of spread
it across the surface, it starts to kind
of clump together or aggregate together.
And the whole reason
why that's happening is.
Well, like this off like the oil
wants to be near itself where it's
considered to be hydrophobic as well,
meaning it's really scared of water.
It's like, Oh, God, you're
not, you're, you're different.
You don't have the same polarity.
We can't, we're not
able to mix as a result.
So when that happens, what we're
going to be seeing is that the protein
is going to fold in a way to help
keep the non polar chains, right?
So the hydrophobic amino acids.
Yeah.
away from water.
So what we're going to see is that
the amino acids that are hydrophobic
will be on the inside of the protein.
All the hydrophilic ones are
going to be on the outside.
So the way that we can actually look at
that, so if I have a sequence of amino
acids, so here is our primary structure,
um, what you're going to be seeing is with
this primary structure that eventually
it's going to get really, really big.
And when it gets a little too big, you're
going to see that it's going to fold.
And now when, how that thing folds.
So if I start with the end terminal again.
You're going to see it kind of fold in
a way where all of the nonpolar regions
are going to be towards the center.
So the hydrophobic ones are, are
yellow, hydrophilic are, are pink.
So what's going to happen is it's
going to fold so that way all the
polar ones are on the outside.
So that way they can interact
with water all around it, right?
Because it's going to have a water shell
all around that protein, surrounding it.
So what you're seeing here is on
the inside is all those hydrophobic
interactions on the inside.
Nonpolar dissolves nonpolar or
interacts with nonpolar in this case.
On the outside, you have all hydrophilic,
so it's like a shell of hydrophilic.
So the way that we like to see the
protein is that when it's in an aqueous
environment, we have a hydrophobic core
and a hydrophilic exterior hydrophilic
shell that are formed around it.
Let's look at our next tertiary
interaction, but let's kind of draw those.
So the first one with hydrophobic, the way
that I like to draw them personally, and
that is, it's a very common way of showing
it is when we look at amino acids, we like
to show how the R groups are interacting.
So the way that I like to personally draw
them myself to make it easy to see is I
like to draw where the backbones are being
turned on their side, and then we draw
the R groups for our different structures.
Thank you So right here I have
phenylalanine and valine, and
what they are doing is they
have a hydrophobic interaction.
They're both all carbons, hydrogens,
being very, very nonpolar.
So we see that these are going
to be what's interacting on
the inside of our protein.
Now when it comes to hydrogen
bonding, what are you looking for?
So this one, it follows
your organic roots, right?
So the way to remember hydrogen
bonding, if you're, if you struggle
with that, is if you remember the
phrase F no to hydrogen bonding, right?
So F no to that, meaning
chlorine, nitrogen, oxygen.
If they are bound to a hydrogen,
they can be a hydrogen bond donor.
All right.
So when we look at these molecules,
what we are seeing is right.
So we have on the left
here, we have an alcohol.
It can be a donor.
On the right hand side we have an amide.
That one can also be a donor as well.
But the way that we have to draw it,
it has to be a, a partial negative,
partial positive, negative, and
then, and then positive, right?
It has to follow that order.
So in this case, the alcohol is
hydrogen bonding towards the amide
group or the nitrogen portion.
So we can see that interaction and
we can label them just like so.
So when we have a salt bridge or an
ionic interaction, this is where the
classification really matters when
you're looking at your amino acids.
So this one, what makes a salt?
You have to think back to like
general chemistry, introductory chem.
What, how do you make a salt?
Well, it's whenever you had an acid
and a base neutralize each other
where you make salt and water.
So whenever we are looking at these,
the way that they, that they're,
that they're going to be working.
Is that you need one of the acidic
amino acids, which is as spartic acid
or glutamic acid, and it has to be
interacting with a basic amino acid,
which is histidine, lysine, or arginine.
Now, the way that that works is it's
all about the acid-based reaction.
So acids donate protons.
So what's gonna happen here is
that the proton that is on the,
on the left hand side from our.
our acid, it's going to
donate it to the base.
So when that happens, right, so if we
were to lose that proton, when it loses
that proton, it's going to be donated
to the amino group on the other side.
So the way that we are actually going to
see this is you actually have a negative
and a positive charge on both sides.
So we'll have a negative on our
carboxylate group, and then we're going
to have a positive on the basic group.
So when that happens, we are forming what
is a salt bridge, or an ionic interaction
that's occurring between the two species.
So it has to be an acid and a base.
So it's that donation of the proton.
So we see that we have an extra
amino, or an extra proton on
our amino group, That is here.
So when we have that one extra proton
that is being shown, it's donating
that and that's the key there.
So whenever we show that you
have to show the charges because
that's the most important.
This is one of the strongest
interactions that exists because we
have that ionic characteristic, right?
That is a strong interaction.
So when that occurs too, so originally
this is aspartic acid on the right.
What happens is the second that
it loses its proton, that's
when it becomes aspartate.
So that a t e ending is when
we refer to when it's an ion.
So if you ever see that and you're
like, where did that a come from?
It doesn't match maybe my
references from my textbook.
A T E tells you that it's ionic.
It's a carboxylate ion.
So just to kind of spell that out.
And then the other one
becomes an ammonium ion.
So when, when we are
seeing that change, right?
So we have an ammonium ion on the right.
Let's take a look at our next one.
With the disulfide linkage, the
way that this one works is that
it must be between cysteines.
So cysteines can be cross
linked to other cysteines.
Meaning that it's going to make
a bond between different parts
of the, of the different protein.
So when this occurs, this is usually
an extracellular chain that's occurring
within these intramolecular forces
that, that's um, in the molecule.
So whenever we're looking at this one,
when I have two cysteines, it's actually
going to go through an oxidation reaction.
One of the most common oxidation is really
with thiol groups, which is an SH group.
So being that cysteine has thiols,
what it's going to do is it's
going to remove the hydrogens.
So when it does that, it's
going to create a covalent bond.
So both hydrogens have to be removed.
And it's going to make an actual bond.
So this is something that can really
help stabilize and lock in the shape
of our molecule when that occurs.
So when it comes to the different
folding that's occurring
in very, very large chains.
So for example, one of the most common
ways that you'll see this one is like you
already look at the structure of insulin.
It has multiple disulfide linkages
that help structure it and help.
Make it a very stable structure to
be able to last quite a long time
and be utilized within the body.
So our last one isn't one that
actually happens between amino acids.
It's actually the interaction
that we talked about earlier,
which was if you remember when you
think of how the protein folds.
Um, when we have these polar side
chains, they're going to be pointing
out a lot of the times towards
the exterior of the molecule.
Now, if you have a polar side chain,
what it can do is, well, just like any
polar molecule, if it has the ability
to hydrogen bond, it can do it, right?
This is in a water environment, so
you're going to see water solvating
anywhere it can because it's
going to get, it's kind of sticky.
It's going to get stuck
on all these molecules.
So anywhere there might be a lone pair
or there might be a hydrogen, water
is going to take advantage of that
and have that hydrophilic interaction.
Okay.
Thanks.
So we're going to have this residual
water solvating and surrounding
all these different proteins.
So that way they're able to be
within solution and to be able
to travel around the body, right?
Can it be, uh, transported
through the bloodstream?
Can it be, uh, brought across,
uh, maybe the cellular membrane?
How can it try to be brought throughout
the different regions of a cell?
This is one way that can help be kind of
transported and carried throughout the
body through a stream of liquid, right?
Now, the last type of example.
Is our quaternary structures and this
video really doesn't focus a lot on
this one, even though it's in the
title, but this one is arguably one of
the most important categories as well.
And it's something I can have a whole
video in its own, but the way that
we classify this one is when you
have multiple polypeptide chains.
So earlier, when we talked about
primary, secondary, tertiary,
those were all together, that
was talking about one chain.
So if you take many of them and you
start kind of folding them together
and bonding them together, either
through disulfide linkages or through
our salt bridges or hydrogen bonding,
it can create a super big complex
that could have a variety of function.
So here is hemoglobin.
So on this one, you can see all
the individual, the multiple
different tertiary structures that
are here and secondary structures.
So you'll see that we
have all of the different.
Alpha helix is to see all the spirals
that are within the structure, you'll
see that there's actually even some
examples of if you look closely,
you'll see some like areas where
there could be pleated sheets in it.
And the thing that's showing here
is there's multiple colored regions.
So you see if there's the two red sections
on the top left and top right, or sorry,
bottom left and top right, and then the
two blue regions, these are four different
subunits all interacting together.
So that way it can help bond and
interact with iron, which would
be kind of in the middle here.
and it will help how it will be able to
transport oxygen throughout the body.
Okay.
So you can kind of imagine this
whole molecule is here just to
transport O2 around your body.
So that way you can be able to
function and breathe and be able
to do all of your functions.
So many amino acids working together
to help transport throughout the body.
Okay.
So this has been my video on
the structures of proteins.
I hope that this video helped you
kind of understand and wrap your head
around all these different definitions.
Um, and if you have any questions, please
listen in the comment section below.
If you have any, uh, the videos that
you would love to see, let me know
and thank you so much for watching.
If this is your first time
here, please hit that like and
subscribe button as always.
And I hope you all have a wonderful day.
I'll see y'all later.
Bye now.